Guide to the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
In the confusing days of the between-War period the SVM called upon board secretaries to help in evaluation of the Movement's role. Responses to a questionnaire sent out by the SVM's 1933 Commission on Policy indicated that some denominations continued to support the idea of a volunteer movement while others did not see a need for it. Representatives of the Baptist and Congregational boards expressed praise for the Movement while the Episcopal, Methodist and Presbyterian representatives were less enthusiastic. Criticism included the statements that "the Movement has dwindled until it is largely a movement of the 'hick' colleges" and "My fear is that at this present stage the idea of volunteering for foreign missions tends to divert the attention of Christian students from the essential obligation of the Christian, whether he goes to the field or stays at home."(SVM Archives, Series V, 1933 Commission.)
Before 1920, most denominations had not sponsored their own student fellowships and the SVM's role on campus had been clear. Partially in reaction to the liberal orientation of the "Y" movements, denominations developed their own campus student groups during the 1920s and 1930s. The effect of this trend was to obscure the SVM's role. According to a SVM report written in 1953, "In the late thirties, the pressure became so strong that SVM was forced to question its very existence, for many of those within the church student movement - - which, by its very nature, was pushing SVM into a separatist movement --- challenged the SVM and said that it should not operate as a separate movement." (SVM Archives, Series V, Board of Directors, April 1933.)
The development of the Student Volunteer Movement's relationship with denominational campus ministries has been touched upon earlier, but here can be mentioned briefly the more direct channels of contact with denominational mission boards which the SVM maintained throughout its existence. When the National Council of Churches of Christ in the United States of America emerged in 1950, the SVM's role in the new organization was as a member Unit of its Division of Foreign Missions, Division of Home Missions and Joint Commission on Missionary Education. The NCCCUSA viewed the SVM as primarily an interdenominational recruiting agency to work among students. As the organization of the National Council of Churches evolved, the SVM became the Missionary Services Department of the Joint Department of Christian Vocation of the Division of Christian Education in 1951. In 1959 when the Volunteer Movement passed from autonomous existence, it was related to the National Council of Churches as the Department of Missionary Services of the Commission on Christian Higher Education.
The SVM and Missions Theory
Various theories regarding missions activity have prevailed in American Protestantism during different historical periods. An early emphasis on evangelization for individual salvation gave way to concentration on church planting and educational work as bases for the spread of the Christian faith. With the rise of indigenous churches overseas the concept of ecumenical sharing gave continued justification for missionary activity. The Laymen's Commission of Appraisal in 1932 proposed a more radical conception of missionary work which involved not only inter-church development but also inter-faith development, drawing on increased appreciation for non-Christian religions. However, in Charles Forman's words, "the reaction of mission boards showed that the mission theory and theology of the Laymen's Commission was not that of American missions."(Forman, p. 103. The 1932 Laymen's Commission report was very controversial in SVM circles. It is mentioned repeatedly in the correspondence and committee minutes of the time.)
When missions activity was no longer viewed as an exporting of Christian civilization, but rather seen as a mode of worldwide ecumenical cooperation, the distinction between foreign missions and home missions became blurred. Throughout the post-World War I era, the Student Volunteer Movement constantly had to justify its continuing specific concentration on foreign missions. The "revolutionaries" of Des Moines in 1920 questioned the appropriateness of sending missionaries abroad when conditions in American were so much in need of Christianization. In a meeting in February of 1920, the Standing Committee discussed at length the pros and cons of Student Volunteer Movement involvement in home missions work, but decided to continue the status quo focus on recruiting for foreign fields only. In 1922, a new home missions movement, the Student Fellowship for Christian Life Service, approached the SVM seeking cooperation; for over a year it used a room in the Movement offices as its headquarters.
Though the issue was discussed many times, it was not until 1945 that the Student Volunteer Movement went beyond cooperation with home missions programs to actual participation in recruiting and educational activity for home fields. It changed its name from the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions to the Student Volunteer Movement for Christian Missions. The announcement of this change noted that:
official action recognizes that the artificial separation of home and foreign missions is now passe', since the work of the
Church, even as the world itself, is one. Whether the distinction between the pioneer, frontier worker on the one hand, and the supporting work on the other, can be or should be maintained for recruitment purposes remains to be seen.(SVM Archives, Series V, 1945 documents: "SVM Prepares for Reconversion of Missionary Enterprise", p. 3.)
The declaration card of the Movement, which formerly had offered only one option, commitment to foreign missions, was revised to offer three alternatives:
I. It is my purpose to become a Christian missionary... at home or... abroad.
II. I propose to seek further guidance regarding the missionary vocation.
III. I propose to support the world mission of the Church through my prayers, gifts and daily work.(SVM Archives, Series V, Board of Directors, 1949.)
This format for the declaration card came under attack from two different angles. Some thought that the Movement was making a mistake in relinquishing its specific focus on foreign missions education and recruitment. They thought that the Movement would become too diffuse and would lose any effectiveness which it still had. At the opposite end of the spectrum, others questioned the entire idea of a declaration card, wondering why the choice of a missionary vocation should be singled out for specific attention, since the Church's mission to the world could be carried out through nearly all vocations.
In 1949 a Committee to Study the Declaration Card was established and it proposed the following format for the card:
... It is my purpose to use my talents and resources to serve the Christian world mission, and in the light of its claims prayerfully to choose my life work.
... Further, it is my purpose, God willing, to be a Christian missionary... at home... abroad.
More than the phrasing of words on a 3" by 5" card was at-stake in discussion of the Student Volunteer Movement declaration of purpose. There was a question of missions theory - how was missionary activity to be distinguished from the normal interrelationships of Christian churches throughout the world? There was the related issue of the membership basis of the SVM --- should it be restricted to individuals who had made a specifically missionary vocational commitment or should a wider base of students, those who were supportive of the Church's world mission, be considered members of the Movement? At a meeting in March 1952, Policy Committee members expressed divergent opinions. E. Fay Campbell felt that "The regular membership of the SVM should be made up of students... who have purposed to offer themselves to Missions Boards for service." Vern Rossman called the first statement on the declaration card "highly problematic." "If we say that every Christian student should be centrally missionary, then every student 'should be' an SVMer." But, in another members opinion, "If one of the prime duties of the Christian community is to point out that almost all vocations can be 'Christian,' then surely the SVM is in a sense defeating the purpose of the Church by creating the feeling that service under a mission board is necessarily more important in the world mission than other vocations."(SVM Archives, Series V, Policy Committee, March 1952.)
As the 1950s progressed and the Student Volunteer Movement became increasingly involved in ecumenical ventures it became clear that the Movement would have a distinct contribution to make to the student Christian scene only if it focused its concerns quite specifically on education and recruitment for world missions service under established mission boards and agencies. The distinction implied by this focus, between the Church's general mission in the world and its "missions",was not agreeable to all, but without such a distinction the need for a Student Volunteer type movement became much less apparent. Those striving to maintain the SVM's distinctiveness felt that the Movement still had a role to play in concentrating on the "frontiers" of the Church mission to the world. There were still many places around the world where strong indigenous churches had not been established and the SVM could help to provide Christian messengers to those areas. Furthermore' it was felt that even the stronger indigenous churches overseas would increasingly welcome the assistance of Western missionaries. As a missionary to China had written to John Mott, "Members of the younger Christian churches have actually taken over the responsibility for determining the future character of the Christian movement and, having worked at this job for a period of years, they now realized its complexity and the need for comradeship."(SVM Archives, Series III, L. Hoover to J. Mott, October 1, 1936.) Another "frontier" which the SVM Newsletter suggested for the Student Volunteer Movement's attention in 1957, was confrontation with atheistic communism.
In the years after the Student Volunteer Movement's merger into the National Student Christian Federation, a Committee for the Fellowship of Student Volunteers produced a monthly newsletter. A large proportion of the articles in these newsletters were related to missions theory, indicating the realization that until these questions of theory were resolved the role of student volunteers could not be clarified. In the May 1960 newsletter there was a call for an "adequate theology of mission."' The problems were evident. "We used to feel that the Church has missions and thought of missions as something which was done for the other People at some distant place. Such an understanding was based on the assumption that Western Christians live in a Christian society and the Christian missionary task was to take our faith and culture to those areas where it was not known."(Newsletter of the Committee for the Fellowship of Student Volunteers, SVM Archives, Series VII, May 1960.) The 1966 dissolution of the Student Volunteer Movement in its guise as the National Student Christian Federation's Commission on World Mission was the logical outcome of an increasingly prevalent theory of mission in liberal American Protestantism, one which stressed the worldwide ecumenical cooperation of the Church rather than focusing on frontier missions of the Western Church to the non-Western world.
The SVM After the Second World War
As indicated by the foregoing, a considerable portion of the Student Volunteer Movement's energy in the post World War II era continued to be taken up in attempts to define its relationships to other student Christian movements and to general Protestant mission mechanics and theory. Despite the uncertainties involved in these evolving relationships, the Movement was able to bounce back from its 1940 nadir and to continue with a positive program for nearly two more decades.
Sydney Ahlstrom, among other historians of American religion, has described a post World War II revival in American Christianity which extended nearly to the end of the 1950s. Amidst social trends of urbanization and suburbanization, geographical mobility, and economic affluence, problems of adjustment and anxieties over status and 'acceptance' were ever-present. Churches were obviously the sort of family institution that the social situation required."(Ahlstrom, p. 951.) The Cold War atmosphere of the era was ripe for the resurgence of a religious faith which could promise peace of mind. Fundamentalist theology which had fallen into disrepute was revived in an intellectually updated form.
During the 1920s and 1930s Student Volunteer Movement leaders had frequently pointed out that the decline of the Movement was directly related to a decline in general interest in religion on American campuses. Students were not likely to commit themselves to missionary work when they were not wholly committed to the Christian faith. A resurgence of more evangelical religion during and after World War II allowed the SVM to find a broader base for its programs. The Board of Directors in 1944 concluded that "The Movement needs to make increasingly clear its commitment to a full evangelical missionary message and program... Not alone in emphasis on current social improvement, but also in and through such service to a message that is in the fullest sense redemptive and eternal, will be its strength."(SVM Archives, Series V, Appendix III, Board of Directors minutes, February 26, 1944.)
In 1946, the Student Volunteer Movement's listing of missionary openings, Christian Horizons, included nearly one thousand overseas vacancies. A publicity release for the Movement claimed that "faced today with the need for hundreds of new workers, both large and small boards look to the Student Volunteer Movement for assistance, both in
supplying candidates to meet immediate needs, and in conducting a program of education and recruitment which will guarantee a steady stream of volunteers from which the boards can select personnel."(SVM Archives, Series V, 1945 document: "SVM Prepares for Reconversion of Missionary Enterprise," p. 1.)
At a meeting of the SVM Board of Directors in April 1948, it was reported that the Movement's finances were in good condition and there were many evidences of increased missionary interest on the campuses. The Movement budget for 1951/1952 was $60,400, more than $10,000 above the budget of the previous year and six times the budget of 1941/1942. During the academic year 1952/1953 a travel staff of twenty men and women from five denominations visited over three hundred colleges in forty-four states on behalf of the Movement.
The resurgence sparked by increased religious interest and the nation's improving economic condition appears to have peaked for the SVM towards the middle of the 1950s, or at least to have taken a different form as the Movement was drawn into ecumenical ventures and faced with theoretical questions about its recruiting program. Twenty-one members of the Movement travel staff visited three hundred and fifty campuses during the academic year 1955/1956. At the same time, however, there were only five hundred declared student volunteers on American undergraduate campuses. The SVM budget for 1956/1957 was reduced to $50,000.
Programs of missionary education and support of student volunteers were carried on after the formation of the National Student Christian Federation by the Commission on World Mission and its Committee for the Fellowship of Student Volunteers. In May 1962 it was reported that the Committee's newsletter was sent to over three thousand volunteers or prospective volunteers. The Commissions program included staff visits to campuses, local Fellowship gatherings of volunteers, Week-End Conversations on Mission, personal encouragement and counseling, Frontier Seminars, the Quadrennial Conference, ecumenical summer service projects, and so forth.
Conclusion It was a long road from the Student Volunteer Movement's visions of heroic service overseas in the late nineteenth century to the Commission on World Mission's decision to dissolve itself in 1966. By 1959 over twenty thousand student volunteers had gone to serve the Church overseas. The Movement had shown repeated resilience in reacting to changing modes of theological expression, mission theory and student thought. Although Arthur Judson Brown's prophecy that the Student Volunteer Movement would be considered as "one of the most remarkable and significant movements in the history of the Church of God" is not likely to be fulfilled, one can perhaps agree with D.W. McWilliams' thoughts at the Movement's twenty-fifth anniversary services:
I think it is no exaggeration to say that the influences that have gone out from these school grounds on which we are gathered this afternoon in some respects have changed the history of the world... I do not think the history of the past twenty-five years can be written without putting in it something about the Student Volunteer Movement which originated here at Mount Hermon.(D.W. McWilliams, "A Reminiscence", The Student Volunteer Movement After Twenty-Five Years, pp. 70-71.)
Scope and Contents
I. Volunteer and inquirer forms and statistics
II. Volunteer and inquirer correspondence
III. General correspondence
IV. Financial correspondence and records
V. Organization and policy records
VI. Field work
VII. Publications and literature distribution
VIII. Conventions
IX. Relationships with other organizations
X. Photographs
The Student Volunteer Movement Board of Directors voted in October of 1943 to transfer the archives of the Movement to the Yale Divinity School Library. Further archival increments were sent to the Library through 1963. A large volume of Volunteer Declaration of Purpose cards were microfilmed by the Library and the originals destroyed. The remainder of the material is in its original, in some cases crumbling, format.
Besides documenting the activities of the Student Volunteer Movement in a very complete way, these archives also provide valuable information on various aspects of American religious life during the period 1886 to 1960. Religious conditions on American college and university campuses are documented. Vast files of student volunteer application and information sheets provide personal data on thousands of prospective missionaries.
These sheets, in addition to health examination blanks for the years 1923 to 1937, provide extensive information of potential interest to genealogists, biographers, and historians. The financial records and correspondence of the Movement provide documentation related to philanthropic support of religious causes in America. In short, the archives are a largely untouched mine of information for the historian of American religious life.
The researcher should be aware of the extent to which the Student Volunteer Movement archives are supplemented by other collections at the Yale Divinity Library. The Library holds the personal papers of various leaders and friends of the Movement including those of its founder and General Secretary (1920-1927) Robert P. Wilder; its longtime Executive Committee chairman and leader, John R. Mott; its first educational secretary Harlan P. Beach; volunteer and committee member Kenneth Scott Latourette; traveling secretary Lyman Hoover; and other supporters of the Movement such as Luther D. Wishard, George Sherwood Eddy, and Clarence P. Shedd. Also found at the Divinity Library are the early archives of the YMCA-Student Division and the World Student Christian Federation, two organizations whose leaders were intimately associated with the Student Volunteer Movement.
As might be expected in the archives of a long-lived and constantly evolving organization like the Student Volunteer Movement, the categories indicated by Series I through X are more clear-cut in theory than in practice. The archives were in a chaotic state due to the circumstances of their accumulation at the Library, inconsistencies in SVM procedures, and previous attempts by untrained Library personnel to organize portions of the material. In the detailed descriptions which follow, an attempt has been made to indicate points of overlap, gaps in documentation, and material of particular interest in each series.
Arrangement
I. Volunteer and inquirer forms and statistics
II. Volunteer and inquirer correspondence
III. General correspondence
IV. Financial correspondence and records
V. Organization and policy records
VI. Field work
VII. Publications and literature distribution
VIII. Conventions
IX. Relationships with other organizations
X. Photographs
College students in missionary work; College students -- Religious life; Missions; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Women in missionary work; Beach, Harlan P. (Harlan Page), 1854-1933; Capan, Edward Warren, 1870-1947; Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963; Judd, Walter H., 1898-1994; Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968; Mackay, John Alexander, 1889-1983; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971; Speer, Robert E. (Robert Elliott), 1867-1947; Van Dusen, Henry P. (Henry Pitney), 1897-1975; Visser 't Hooft, Willem Adolph, 1900-1985; Warnshuis, A. L. (Abbe Livingston), 1877-1958; Wilder, Robert P., 1863-1938; Zwemer, Samuel Marinus, 1867-1952; National Student Christian Federation; Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions
- Volunteer and Inquirer Forms and Statistics, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Included in Series I are the forms and record keeping devices used by the Student Volunteer Movement to keep track of its members and prospective members. The enormity of the Movement's record-keeping task becomes apparent when one considers that by 1932, 48,866 individuals had volunteered and many non-volunteers were also on the Movement's mailing lists. There are over fifty linear feet of records in Series I, dating from approximately 1888 to 1956. The material is divided according to the following formats
  A. Declaration' information and Address cards
  1. Declaration cards: In order to become a member of the Student Volunteer Movement, a student was expected to sign a declaration of purpose card and complete a follow-up information blank. The wording and explanatory material on the declaration of purpose card were changed several times during the Movement's existence but the centrality of this written commitment remained constant. From the card's earliest phrasing, "I am willing and desirous, God permitting, to become a foreign missionary", to its later two and three option formats, the formal declaration of purpose was thought to be an effective means of crystallizing nebulous missionary interest into productive missionary action. Thousands of declaration of purpose cards are found in the Movement archives. Those from the period 1888 to 1922 have been microfilmed and the originals destroyed. The over fifteen hundred cards available for the period 1941 to 1953, in addition to the signed declaration, also provide basic information about the volunteer, including his or her address, academic affiliation and area of study, denominational ties, and so forth. The declaration cards on microfilm and those from the period 1923 to 1941 are arranged first by the year in which the card was signed and within each year in two alphabetical sequences, for men and women respectively. The later cards are arranged alphabetically in two blocks. The first "A" to "Z" sequence includes cards signed during the years c.1941 to 1949. The second "A" to "Z" sequence includes cards signed during the years c.1945 to 1953.